Guide to the Geoffrey Cornell Hazard Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Geoffrey Cornell Hazard Papers
1947-1978
MS 1346
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3
(7 boxes)
Correspondence, notes, drafts, clippings of cases from court reporters, all relating to Hazard's work as principal writer of Restatement of the Law: Second Judgements (St. Paul, American Law Institute Publishers, 1982).
Hazard, Geoffrey C., Jr., 1929-2018
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Geoffrey C. Hazard, 1982.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains, almost exclusively, materials relating to Hazard's work on the American Law Institute's book, Restatement of the Law: Second Judgments (St. Paul: ALI Publishers, 1982), 3 vols. This book is part of an ongoing series of Restatements published by ALI, which seek to restate and clarify legal principles and current practice for the benefit of courts and other practicioners. The first series of restatements began in 1932 and comprised 19 volumes. The volumes on Judgments were published in 1942. The second series began in 1953 as a revision and extension of the first series. Starting in 1973 Hazard served as a 'reporter,' or principal writer, of the second restatement of judgments.
The Restatement on Judgments concerns the doctrine of res judicata, the rule that a judgment may preclude later relitigation of the same or related issues or claims in a different trial. Although this doctrine has some application to criminal law, it is most often applied in civil cases, and therefore this Restatement concerns only civil actions. The Restatement is organized into six chapters: (1) an introduction, (2) the validity of a judgment, (3) what sort of binding effect a judgment may have, (4) the effect of a judgment on those who were not parties to it, (5) how to obtain relief from a judgment and (6) what problems arise when a judgment of one type of tribunal, e.g., an administrative agency or arbitration tribunal, is to be applied by a different type of tribunal. This Restatement does not concern the application of the judgments of one state in a different state; these fall into the area of Conflicts of Law. The Law of Judgments therefore generally concerns the validity and legal impact within a state of a legal judgment once it is issued, rather than the process leading up to a judgment.
The files in this collection hold correspondence, hand written notes and drafts, and numerous clippings of cases from court reporters, all pertaining to Hazard's work on Judgments Restatement, Second. The numbers on many folders, which are often preceded by the symbol correspond to the sections of the book dealing with specific points of law.
Biographical / Historical
Geoffrey C. Hazard Jr. was born in 1929, received his B.A. from Swarthmore College in 1953, and his LL.B. from Columbia Law School in 1954, where he was an editor of the Law Review.
After graduation from law school, Hazard was admitted to the Oregon Bar and practiced law with the firm of Hart, Spencer, McCulloch and Rockwood in Portland. In 1957 he was appointed Executive Secretary of the Oregon Legislative Interim Committee on Judicial Administration. One year later he became an Associate Professor of Law at the University of California, Berkeley. In 1961 he was promoted to Professor, a post which he held for three years before becoming a Professor at the University of Chicago in 1964. Hazard taught for seven years at Chicago, and from 1964 to 1970 he was also Executive Director of the American Bar Foundation.
Hazard first came to Yale as a Visiting Professor for the academic year 1970-1971. The following year (1971) Yale appointed him as a Professor of Law, and in 1979 he was named the John A. Garver Professor, and in 1986 was appointed Sterling Professor of Law. He also served as Associate Dean of Yale's School of Organization and Management (SOM) from 1980 to 1981. After leaving Yale in 1994 he served as Trustee Professor of Law at the University of Pennsylvania until 2009, when he joined the faculty at the University of California Hastings College of the Law.
Hazard was also a member and former director (from 1984 to 1999) of the American Law Institute (ALI) and a Fellow of the American Bar Foundation. From 1971 to 1977 he served as a 'reporter' for the American Bar Association's Committee on Standards of Judicial Administration. He also served on the ABA's Committee on Professional Standards, and starting in 1973 was a 'reporter' for the ALI's Judgments Restatement second project. The materials in this collection deal with this project.
Hazard taught administrative law and civil procedure, among other subjects. He published numerous books and articles, including Challenges to Legal Education, 1968; Civil Procedure (with Fleming James) 1977; Ethics in the Practice of Law, 1978; and Cases and Materials on Pleading and Procedure: State and Federal (with David W. Louiselle), 1979. Hazard died on January 11, 2018.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Judgments; Law; Lawyers; Hazard, Geoffrey C., Jr., 1929-2018; American Law Institute
- Inventory
  - Carroll, John D. III, ALI Research Asst., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence re: Rule 23, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence re: Rule 41, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - ALI Restatement 2nd Judgments (1), 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Restatement of Judgments 2nd (2), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Restatement of Judgments 2nd (3), 1973-1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Restatement of Judgments 2nd (4), 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Restatement Comments on TD #5, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Restatement of Judgments Group, 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Chapter 1 (1) General Principles, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Chapter 2 (2) Jurisdiction: Introductory Note, 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 3 Competence, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 4 (empty), undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 5 Notice, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 6 Objection to Competence of the Court, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 7 Objection to the Competence of the Court: Party who does not appear, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - 8 Objection to Territorial Jurisdiction of a Court: Special and Limited Appearances, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - 9 Objection to Notice: Special Appearance, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - 10 Objection to Territorial Jurisdiction of a Court: Party who does not appear, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 11 Adjudication of an Objection to Competence, Territorial Jurisdiction, or Notice, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - 12 Applicable Law of the Res Judicata, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - 41-41.3 Finality, 1974-1976, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 42. 42.1, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 46 State Judgments Involving Federal Question, 1975-1976 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - 45-48.1 Merger, Bar, Claim Preclusion, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - 56-56.1 Counterclaims, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - 60(b), 1974-1976 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - 61-61.2 "Claim", 1973-1978 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - 62, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - 68-68.1 Issue Preclusion, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 30-31)
  - 73 In Rem, 1973-1975 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - 74 Status, 1973, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - 75 Garnishment, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - 76 Declaratory Judgments, 1974-1976 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - 77a Administrative Agency Determinations, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - 77b Arbitration (?), 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - 77c, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - 77d, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - 77e, undated (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - 78 Parties: Scope of Participation, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - 79 Incapacity, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - 80 Different Capacities, 1974-1977 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - 81 Nominal Parties (empty), undated (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - 82 Aligned on Same Side, 1972-1973, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - 83 Person Controlling, 1973, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - 84 Agreeing To Be Bound (empty), undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - 85-86 Represented By Party, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - 87 Bailor/Bailee, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - 88 Bernhardt Rule, 1975-1978 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - 89-90 Successors in Interest, 1972, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - 91 Persons Bound By Injunctions, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - 92 Survival, Wrongful Death, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - 93 Members of a Family, 1972-1973, 1975-1977 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - 94 Judgments, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - 95 Discharge of Judgment, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - 99 and Introd. Restatement of Judgments, 1975-1977 (Box 5, Folder 57-58)
  - 101 Co-Obligors, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - 102 Co-Obligors, undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - 103 Co-Owners, undated (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - 104 Assignee/Assignor, 1975-1976 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - 105 Third Party Contract Beneficiaries, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - 107 Non-insurance Indemnitors, 1975, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - 107.1 Insurer/Insured, 1973-1977 (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - 108 Restatement, 1976-1977 (Box 6, Folder 66-67)
  - 109 Restatement, 1975-1976 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - 110 Unincorporated Associations Notes - Peter Shane, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - 111 Estoppel of Non-Party to Assert Claim, 1975-1977 (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - llla 1978 (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - 112 1976 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - 113 1976 (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - 115 1975 (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - 116 1976 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - 117 1976 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - 118 1976 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - 150 Criminal Cases, 1973-1977 (Box 7, Folder 78-80)
  - 160 Arbitration, 1975-1978 (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - 161 1976 (Box 7, Folder 82)